<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bruce Dawson</title>
    <link>https://www.bruce.audio/</link>
    <description>Recent posts from on Bruce Dawson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 21:03:02 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.bruce.audio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How&#39;d we get here?</title>
      <link>https://www.bruce.audio/post/helloworld/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 21:03:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bruce.audio/post/helloworld/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How&amp;rsquo;d we get here, what&amp;rsquo;s the plan, and where have I been?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;_today-things-feel-different-and-im-okay-with-that_&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;today things feel different and I&amp;rsquo;m okay with that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I&amp;rsquo;d like to welcome you and mention that I plan to use this space to provide life updates on occasion, discuss interesting engineering problems I am solving, and discuss digital audio. Subscribe via &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:hi@bruce.audio?subject=I%20want%20to%20subscribe!&#34;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bruce.audio/index.xml&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;rsquo;d like to receive automatic updates when I create new posts on this blog. Second, I&amp;rsquo;d like to address that I spent the past few months radio-silent on social media after finding myself in deep need of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://health.clevelandclinic.org/digital-detox/&#34;&gt;digital detox&lt;/a&gt; and a desire to find some balance in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past six months of my life has been interesting. For over a decade I spent so much of my time
dedicated to my craft of playing music &amp;ndash; primarily electronic music in the form of
techno and psy-trance. While I&amp;rsquo;ll always have a natural affinity for this type of music, I haven&amp;rsquo;t
found playing music to be the primary source of fulfillment that it once was. It&amp;rsquo;ll always
remain a part of me, but somehow, today things feel different and I&amp;rsquo;m okay with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;_i-had-to-make-a-decision_&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I had to make a decision.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, I had been striving toward a fantasy of being a globetrotting DJ while having a family and thriving in my professional career as a software engineer. My music career would fluctuate over the years, as I&amp;rsquo;d play a number of events each festival season &amp;ndash;
mostly locally, but some bookings would occur in nearby states (including a few times playing in Mexico). It dawned on me one day that in order to thrive as a performing musician, one must give it a
full-hearted effort (no shit, right?). Admittedly, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been as invested in the craft as my peers and I knew it. Conversely, it had also dawned on me that I had a considerable amount of opportunity in front of me as a software engineer. This opportunity, also admittedly, had been taken for granted. In retrospect, I had spent far too much energy on pursuing opportunities that required immense amounts of effort, networking, and luck to achieve, all the while doing nothing to take true ownership over the opportunities directly in front of me within my professional career. I had to make a decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While doing this soul-searching I had realized that both of these crafts that I am deeply
passionate about required a thorough effort to thrive in their respective domains. I had seen
that, while I continued to pursue my ambitions of being a musician, the sheer amount of work
that goes into becoming a successful musician parallels (and in a lot of way, exceeds) the amount of effort it takes to be a successful software engineer and contributor to the tech community. One of these crafts involves late-night networking in downtown warehouses, bars, and clubs, weekend-after-weekend while the other involves involves community involvement through open-source contributions, technical talks, tutoring, and so forth. Either is going to be difficult, but which choice brings the truest sense of fulfillment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;_the-only-thing-ive-known-and-loved-longer-in-my-life-than-electronic-music-is-programming_&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The only thing I&amp;rsquo;ve known and loved longer in my life than electronic music is programming.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had also started therapy in these months of radio-silence, found some tools that work for me, and turned my attention inward. I&amp;rsquo;ve found it deeply impactful and has really helped me reframe the
inner-dialog around what brings me true fulfillment. While I&amp;rsquo;ll always love music, and I&amp;rsquo;ll happily share it with others when the opportunity is right, I also know where my heart is invested, and I know what keeps the creative flame alive inside. The only thing I&amp;rsquo;ve known and loved longer in my life than electronic music is programming. Today pursing this path with a full-hearted effort is invigorating. Today taking ownership over the opportunities staring me in the face
is fulfilling. Doing what I can to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kadenze.com/programs/output-teaches-creating-audio-plugins-with-c-and-juce&#34;&gt;lower the bar to entry&lt;/a&gt; for my peers brings me so much satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;_it-was-a-revealing-and-impactful-exploration_&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;It was a revealing and impactful exploration..&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, toward the end of last year I decided to dive head-first in relearning the fundamentals of
computer science. Why would I do that? Well, I wanted to take ownership over the knowledge gaps in my understanding and do a thorough pass through all the information I should be expected to know &amp;ndash;  fundamental data structures, algorithms, design patterns, asymptotic complexity, and so on. It was a revealing, humbling, and impactful exploration, one of which I will dive into further in depth here in an upcoming post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then friends, thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
